<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Nathan Hughes' blog</title><link>https://sirsharpest.github.io/</link><description>A blog ranting about my research, personal projects and all that I find interesting</description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" rel="self" href="https://sirsharpest.github.io/rss.xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:nathan1hughes@gmail.com"&gt;Nathan Hughes&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 23:46:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Fallacy of Robust Science</title><link>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/the-fallacy-of-robust-science/</link><dc:creator>Nathan Hughes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orgddcc4f8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgddcc4f8"&gt;Part 1: The Best-laid schemes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgddcc4f8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Scientific experiments &lt;b&gt;should&lt;/b&gt; be performed with ruthless accuracy, with excellent logbooks and note keeping on all details which could have any impact on the results (no matter how insignificant a detail it may seem). This is agreed upon by all scientific practitioners. Otherwise how could results ever be trusted? How could anyone ever be expected to believe something vaguely described?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Furthermore, how can anyone ever look at their work, at the thing they spend 36+ hours a week on, the thing they spend more time with than their family at times and have an objective view on? Does this mean that the people best qualified to perform research are also the worst to form ideas on it?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org928b048" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org928b048"&gt;Repeatably&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org928b048"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Consistently demonstrating that for all observations under a specific set of parameters, that &lt;i&gt;X&lt;/i&gt; occurs and has &lt;i&gt;Y&lt;/i&gt; traits; A set of instructions, which could be passed to another in the same area and allow them to reproduce and discover the same findings. This is what (some) scientists consider to be an informative and useful contribution.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These statements can be easily read, with many a vigorous head-nod and "of courses", but really, how can such rigid ideas be used as a tool to fight against the chimera which is the natural world, the universe we so desperately want to understand just the tiniest bit. A thing so huge, vast and unbelievable that even our most sophisticated hypothesis are regularly retracted, updated and doubted on.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The issues which can prevent repeatably could be anything from requiring the exact same sequence prior events to occur, to rare materials or instruments which can not feasibly be acquired again for reasons outside of a researchers control.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Time and expiration of same is another great enemy of the hypothesis. We can grow a set of plants in a field one year, but if we decide to repeat the experiment the weather will not care and it continue to provide a unique sequence of conditions, different to what came before.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Taking the idea of reproducibility to the extreme: A simple hypothesis could suggest that each time you drop a pencil from 1 meter above the floor that it will ultimately make contact with the floor below it. This is an easy to test idea, this could be tested twice, a hundred times or even many thousand times. BUT! Never can this be tested for all possible times, it is strictly impossible to test this for all times which could exist and have existed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How can we be sure of results which cannot be repeated, and repeated, and repeated?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
How can we ever be satisfied with the ease, or even the number of times a hypothesis has been tested?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org90be24b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org90be24b"&gt;The Formidable Bias&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org90be24b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Sherlock Holmes said that "It is an error to argue in front of your data. You can find yourself insensibly twisting them round to suit your theories". Sir Arthur Conan Doyle had a remarkable gift for explaining, and giving evidence towards, the naivety of us humans…
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In research the Null-Hypothesis is used in a veiled attempt to turn bias on its head. A search should not be to prove that an idea is right, but rather to prove that it is wrong. A noble endeavour, to seek ones own defeat, but really a rare occurrence. Proof of this? The lack of approval by the scientific community, where are the journals for publishing insignificant experiment findings, where are the prizes for robustness and dedication to pursuing truth over funding grants?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Wanting to be wrong in your assumptions and hypothesis is one thing, but when that would also come at the cost of a promotion, of a funding approval or even keeping a job. It almost makes perfect sense then why null-hypothesis testing, whilst experiments 101, is a fable.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;div id="org2a0ff85" class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://sirsharpest.github.io/images/evidence.jpg" alt="evidence.jpg" width="50%" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;A desire to be right&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Furthermore, ideas about knowledge and expectations can bring more bias and more issues. The contrast in wanting to be proven wrong and using agnostic evidence to keep beliefs alive, is staggering. Not unlike the human vision system's remarkable methods for filling in gaps and enabling optical illusions, so too will minds craft connections which are feeble at best, to push ideas.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Does there exist such a person who is so humble that they can easily admit to being wrong, when they dedicate their life to becoming a renowned expert in a field? A difficult feat at the best of times. What funding body, tax-payer or investor is willing to hear that the  breakthrough they desired is not coming. It may not even be possible. It becomes easy understand how a (un)conscious bias can form and jeopardise an experiment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>science research</category><guid>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/the-fallacy-of-robust-science/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 20 Apr 2018 22:45:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Ramble About ELisp</title><link>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/a-ramble-about-elisp/</link><dc:creator>Nathan Hughes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org82129b5" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org82129b5"&gt;My current language situation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org82129b5"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
My first programming language was C++, about 11 years ago I picked up the book "C++ for dummies". Like many teenagers I wanted to make my own games and every resource I came across told me that I would need to learn C++. So I did.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For about 7 of those years I developed solely in C/C++ only ever using Java, HTML and JavaScript for assignments at college. To me I was a person who only cared about efficiency and therefore all other languages were a distraction from creating smooth and lightweight applications.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
It was about 3/4 years ago now that I picked up Python as a language, I wanted to scrape websites to get pdf documents which were behind verbose menus and godawful UIs (ahem BlackBoard). I reasoned with myself that Python was a good addition to my kit as it provided a "get it done quickly" tool, I ended up using it more and more. Now all of my work is Python based, all of my analysis is dependant on Python libraries (Matplotlib, Pandas, Scipy etc.).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
My point of this initial rant is that I created an annoying situation for myself. When presented with a challenge or task I would consider these two options:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I want it written quickly? - Use Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do I want it to perform efficiently - Use C/C++&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As someone who genuinely loves programming and playing with new languages, this became annoying. I could no longer find motivation to learn another language well. There was no benefit to me. Sure there are arguments, but for something to impact my work, my hobbies or my efficiency there was no real contender.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org7cf11ec" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org7cf11ec"&gt;Along comes emacs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org7cf11ec"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I'll spare the story about how emacs changed my life and I was saved from a life of cumbersome IDEs. The short of it is, emacs became my editor around the same time I picked up Python.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A few months ago however I started to truly love emacs, building an editor to be exactly what I needed and wanted. I changed the way that I thought about the code I was writing. It clicked with me that the code itself was just data and so much of the work is how we think about it and manipulate it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org1bd215b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org1bd215b"&gt;elisp&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org1bd215b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Emacs isn't a text editor. It's a lisp interpreter, it just happens to be a great editor when you toy with it enough (paraphrasing the old operating system joke there!).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Really though, this is true. Emacs has given me something which I was wanting for so long. A solid reason to learn a language which I could incorporate into my daily work routine, something which would make me better at my tasks.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A great example (to me) of this is my first elisp function:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;dear-diary&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="s"&gt;"This function can be used to create an org file with today as it's file name."&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;find-file&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;concat&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"~/Dropbox/Notes/"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;format-time-string&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"%Y-%m-%d.org"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;))))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For anyone unfamiliar with elisp, it simply opens a file with today's date in my dropbox. It's something I use almost everyday to keep track of what I've done and what I need to follow up on with my projects.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This code however, is nothing to some of the amazing things that other people create!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;A bigger bang-for-your-buck demo of CSV transpose &lt;a href="https://t.co/Z3fTYmOhQP"&gt;pic.twitter.com/Z3fTYmOhQP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— emacs gifs (@emacs_gifs) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/emacs_gifs/status/784248191851954177?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;October 7, 2016&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
This beautiful example of transposing a CSV file is just one example I came across the other day.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Maybe it's simple, but writing code which changes how we code is something that I am endlessly fascinated by.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>emacs</category><category>programming</category><guid>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/a-ramble-about-elisp/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 23:09:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Dissertation Update</title><link>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/dissertation-update/</link><dc:creator>Nathan Hughes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-orge9c4d27" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orge9c4d27"&gt;What am I working on?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orge9c4d27"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In sort I am trying to model how the morphometric traits of various genotypes of wheat interact.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To do this I'm using µ-CT image analysis to find and extract the 3D traits of wheat seeds.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org400fd8b" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org400fd8b"&gt;Types of wheat being used and their ploidy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org400fd8b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The types of wheat being used in this study are:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wild Monococcum (2N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Domesticated Monococcum (2N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tauschii (2N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Durum (4N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dicoccoides (4N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dicoccum (4N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ispahanicum (4N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Timopheevii (4N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spelta(6N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aestivum (6N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compactum (6N)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org2b6221b" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org2b6221b"&gt;What's the status?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org2b6221b"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Currently I'm in the stage of writing up my results and also trying to find more biologically significant information
in the data that I've gathered.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Our methods for finding meaning have become rather primitive as the below image demonstrates :) myself and a few others searched
through my graphs in the office the other day to see if anything jumped out at us for further exploration. I can't be sharing data yet, but a lot of things have become more interesting and we are very eager to explore!
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;div id="org225a80e" class="figure"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://sirsharpest.github.io/images/floor.jpg" alt="floor.jpg" width="100%" align="center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="figure-number"&gt;Figure 1: &lt;/span&gt;Graphs galore!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dissertation</category><category>research</category><guid>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/dissertation-update/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 08 Apr 2018 00:33:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Read CSVs to org tables</title><link>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/csvs-to-org-tables/</link><dc:creator>Nathan Hughes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org67d15fd" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org67d15fd"&gt;Turning CSV files into beautiful org-mode tables&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org67d15fd"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One thing I find myself doing a lot is working with CSV (comma separated value) files, I store a lot of my data in them. I also find that I need to edit them a lot, or check the values in them. I generally then want to use them in reports that I write, at least I like to put in samples of the data to give readers an indication of what I'm talking about.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Since I write almost everything in org-mode these days I wrote this little function, partially to teach myself more elisp and partially because it actually is useful for me day to day.
It simply takes a file location from the user and formats a nice org mode style table.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org2cb4c87" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org2cb4c87"&gt;Elisp code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org2cb4c87"&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;defun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;org-read-csv&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;interactive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;progn&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;find-file&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;read-file-name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"CSV location:"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;org-mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;goto-char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;point-min&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;insert&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"|"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;re-search-forward&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"\n"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;replace-match&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"|\n|"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;delete-char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;-1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;re-search-backward&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;","&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;nil&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nv"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;replace-match&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;"|"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nf"&gt;org-table-align&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;))&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>coding</category><category>emacs</category><guid>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/csvs-to-org-tables/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 22:04:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Call me Ishmael</title><link>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/call-me-ishmael/</link><dc:creator>Nathan Hughes</dc:creator><description>&lt;div id="outline-container-org303f8b8" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org303f8b8"&gt;Where am I?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org303f8b8"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This is my &lt;b&gt;brand&lt;/b&gt; new blog, problems with my past hosting service, a nauseating CMS (wordpress) and a desire to write my rants in the beautiful org-mode led me to creating this site.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgf14a798" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgf14a798"&gt;What's it for?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgf14a798"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What's any blog for really?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Mostly I wanted a method of informally discussing my current projects and interests and possibly write a tutorial or two as well.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blog</category><category>rant</category><guid>https://sirsharpest.github.io/posts/call-me-ishmael/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 07 Apr 2018 21:17:15 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>